knowledge is power
[Music]
hello hi jake hello hi sandy how are you
how you doing that's a really dope
background you got there well you like
it thank you yeah it's uh
adjusting to a smaller room i thought it
was kind of strange to have my bed in
such a
obvious site but here oh i actually
didn't notice that it was your bed at
all
it looks like a couch in the background
and i love that you have einstein there
someone actually asked me on a podcast
interview last week if i could
go back in history and have
lunch with someone who would it be and i
said einstein and it was einstein i like
that choice what do you think that you
would legitimately ask him like if you
were like your first question he's just
sitting there waiting for you at the
table what would you even say
yeah that's such a good question i don't
know i feel like
i feel like one of the things that
intrigues me the most about him
is how
like he seems like a very uh
like a crazy person right and and i
think what fascinates me about that is
that it's typically the people who are
quote-unquote crazy and are out of this
world that can get us somewhere so i i i
just i'm just curious about like how
he
lives like how how do you manage his
personal life with the work that he does
you know like yeah how did how did he
how did he do all that you know
especially when you're being so known
for the work that you do like how do you
manage your own personal life i just
find that kind of interesting yeah yeah
because now you know we think of he's
this legend now he's he's an icon in a
way you know he's i'm gonna have posters
of him on my wall you know so he is like
this pop culture thing almost but even
just in that time i wonder how different
it was for him too you know like if they
really saw him obviously he was you know
proposing things um that were changing
our the way we looked at reality at its
very core
but i kind of wonder if he if a lot of
people just kind of kept thinking he was
crazy most the time and then it was not
till an afterthought where they're like
okay actually that was pretty profound
what he was doing and thinking
yeah because i think like in the world
that we live in today there's so many
different
uh
like with the social media and
everything like that there's so many
different ways that you can view
yourself and sometimes when you're so
deep in your own work as an expert you
know and then you have your personal
life as well i feel like people go
through this identity
these identity um
like not knowing what to identify as and
i'm just curious with einstein like what
what that was like for him
you know yeah yeah i mean imagine what
once his theories are are taken
seriously and then they're proposed into
the scientific community like how would
you not be so ultra aware of well i'm
i'm the guy
yeah you would be you would become that
identity it and be hard not to so yeah
it would be super cool to talk to him
yeah
yeah well i'm excited that we're
connecting those that's a cool start
yeah definitely yeah hey anybody who who
likes einstein i'm usually pronto i i
think that for me
um because i've got like a couple
einstein shirts and stuff too
i don't know and i'm not i'm not someone
who can like recite everything he's ever
said um i just i'm so fascinated by
someone who
sees the world and goes huh like i
wonder if there's an answer to it i
wonder if that's something i could solve
or you know just someone who's using
their ideas or their intellect or their
inner you know thought patterns to
to decipher the world around them is
just so so cool to me to like push
against those boundaries
yeah well i love what your like the
summer of your podcast says it's like
exploring the galaxies of human
connections and understanding perception
right like that's why people like him
are so fascinating to me because it
takes someone who is very courageous and
brave
to
challenge the status quo or to challenge
what's what's normal
and to actually challenge the entire
world to start viewing things a lot
differently as well
like he must have been very very crazy
you know during those times but today
you and i are sitting down together
right now and we don't even know him
personally or anything but we're talking
about him right so it's just it makes me
think about like how can we bring forth
more trailblazers and people who think
out of the box and and people who are
willing to challenge what we're being
told or what we're being taught which i
think is so important in the times that
we're living in right now like i can't
stress that enough yeah i mean i mean
100 though i think we're we're doing our
best by you know by having the
conversations out loud and you know by
you being your authentic selves it gives
permission for other people to do the
same you know yeah sometimes just by us
uh you know living as close as we can or
living from that like center being
within ourselves so you can spark
something within other people it ushers
that epiphany in within other people and
then they're given permission
yeah that's so true yeah yeah um hey so
let's uh let's back up a little bit
sandy welcome to the junkyard love
podcast um
i was really excited uh reading your bio
and everything so let's just start with
uh i have a few notes there's a lot of
cool stuff and i was listening to these
on some podcasts and uh i really like a
lot of your perspective so let's just
start with a bio um kind of what got you
to where you are what do you do
um yeah what is it what it is that you
do
yeah
yeah well i'm sandy i am a fiance a dog
mom
a big sister to some two younger
siblings um daughter of two immigrants
first generation
asian american
my background is vietnamese
black and indian it's typically one of
the first questions that i get
when i walk outside the door is i always
have people approach me and ask what my
ethnicity is so i i like to i like to
talk about that
and
i am a meditation teacher practitioner
and i have an online wellness practice
where i work with individuals to guide
them back to their center
and and help them to awaken to the
wholeness that they already are i think
a lot of times especially through my own
personal journey
one of the things that i've learned is
that
we
receive what i call so much of external
programming in our lives that we absorb
that to be true and we make it our
identities so for me when i was in
college i absorbed this external
programming this identity of i need to
work really hard because my parents are
immigrants they were both very poor in
vietnam and they didn't have you know a
lot to live on and had really big
families as well and wow like now they
went through so much to get me
to give birth to me over here in america
and i have to give back to them and so i
grew up with that type of mentality so
it added a lot of pressure on me on a
very early age that i didn't know
was pressure i just thought it was the
right thing to do
and so when i was in my early college
years
there were a multiple series of events
that were very painful that happened
around all at the same time
you know my dad had left the family
and i'm very close to my dad so it was
very heartbreaking how
the dynamics between him and my mom bled
led for that to happen
and
my cousin lena who i'm the closest to
passed away from leukemia and at that
time i was in a long-term relationship
and
that ended as well and so i just felt
like i gave so much of myself to the
outer world and then when it came down
to it i felt like i had nothing and
nobody everyone just left and um it
brought me down this this road of deep
depression to where i thought that the
only way that i would get out of feeling
this pain that i eventually got addicted
to feeling was to take my own life
and it was through that journey that i
became awakened to a higher sense of
consciousness and that there actually is
so much more to life than what meets the
eye
and that you know 99
of the world are full of things that we
actually don't see that's controlling
the way that we lead our lives versus
what we do see and so i started to shift
my entire perspective of not just seeing
what was physical in front of me
uh and and making that be true for
example i gained 40 pounds 40 extra
pounds on my body my dad left you know
those are all physical things that were
happening in front of me that i deemed
to be true
and i adopted this identity of a
depressed person that was also a rock
star hustler and got so many things done
at the same time
versus recognizing that there's so much
in the unseen world like the fact that
we are also one with the divine and and
just exploring even more of what that
means so that's where my my journey
eventually led me to become a meditation
teacher and you know i went from
thinking that i would be this
badass rock star rocking you know hot
pink suits in new york city doing public
relations to you know being barefooted
most of the time still working with
high achieving people but now i'm on the
opposite spectrum where um i work in
wellness and and i guide people back to
their truth and back to their center
wow incredible what what a journey um
okay so it's safe to say that you didn't
plan originally for to to be a
meditation teacher or to you know be
studying consciousness or any of this
sort of stuff
no not at all you know if i you know
it's interesting i would invite everyone
to do this if you look at what you're
doing right now and then you look back
in the earlier years of your life you'll
be able to
you'll be able to observe yourself like
i call it time traveling where you time
travel back to your past you just watch
it like a movie you can observe yourself
doing things where you're like okay i
see where what i'm doing right now
completely makes sense and it all lines
up you know um
but
now when i look at it i can see where it
does line up but
at the time i never consciously said to
myself that one day i'm gonna be a
meditation teacher absolutely so far
removed yeah
yeah uh yeah wow it's it's so crazy
because uh so i resonate with a lot of
what you said i actually had my own
version of
i mean i mean at the time i would call
it an ego death and then after a while i
think i referred to it as a spiritual
awakening um and then after you know
it's it almost seems like this this
you know three year long mushroom trip
or something that i'm finally kind of
coming out of and so i'm i'm doing the
the journaling now you know i'm like
okay what did i actually learn i'm not
experiencing the craziness of it um and
it's so interesting i mean it's
something that really fascinates me this
spiritual awakening um this
are like not just learning about the
egos but um
going from what i would call an ego
death and then after a while i'm like oh
okay so i understand the ego a little
bit differently what is the ego when did
it come about why would i want to kill
it what does that mean to kill it and
then after a while i have this uh
i i like to write a lot of music and i
have this line that's the ego don't like
change or grit but loves to feel
withhold
and then
and i right like uh
i don't know
so so the progression of like learning
about your ego and what it is learning
about your awareness and your perception
and your sense of self and your um who
you are and what your purpose is if
there's such a thing
how to gain meaning from our path you
know this was so so new to me so like i
would have never thought about these
things when i was younger you know ages
you know
young kid to
you know my early 20s i i like i would
have kind of just jokingly not taken
these things seriously it was just in
the realm of religion which i'm like i'm
not a religious person so like cool be
you whatever i don't care but it's just
not for me um
so so what is it so so you went through
similar experience um
like
what what do you so so what is the
spiritual awakening how about that let's
start with that i mean if we could just
do a a broad brushstroke blanket
statement and then you maybe explain how
yours was
yeah a spiritual awakening is waking up
to your spiritual nature uh we are
humans we're having a human experience
but we're spirits so we're spirits
having a human experience and we're here
to have the human experience we're not
here to learn how to be spiritual we're
here to learn how to be human and that's
really the journey of our lives and so a
lot of times when people go through
these spiritual awakening you know you
some people you know they get deep into
a conspiracy realm and then i think
there's like stages to this you get
really deep into conspiracy realm you
start kind of questioning everything
around you you get really deep into you
know some people go to like different
types of plant medicines and and things
like that but you know ultimately i talk
about grounded spirituality because
groundedness is grounded spirituality is
recognizing that you are a spirit having
a human experience and you are here to
learn and practice how to be human and
so if you can wake up to your spiritual
nature it's gonna guide you a lot easier
you're gonna be guided in a way where
you don't feel so overwhelmed and
confused and lost all the time because
you're being one with the divine
you're being one with your higher self
whereas if you weren't awakened to your
spiritual nature you think that you are
only human and when you think that
you're only human you think that you are
subject to pain you are subject to um
you know dis-ease and this is how your
life is going to be so for example
when i had depression i just thought
that this was how my life was going to
be at that time i adopted this victim
consciousness where so much of the way
that i was thinking was coming from the
unconscious portion of my mind i
believed that i was going to feel this
way forever to such a degree that i
thought that the only thing that would
take this pain away was if i took my own
life right and and so
when you understand that you are spirit
having a human experience you recognize
that yes i am this human
i identify as you know you know jake the
podcast host or sandy the meditation
teacher however i'm also having i'm also
a spirit as well i'm beyond what just
what my body is i'm beyond my mind and
beyond my thoughts so if i were to put
that in a blanket statement that's what
i would say a spiritual awakening is
it's waking up to your true nature and
and just allowing all the things that
aren't not you to
fall away
wow wow wow yeah that's great um yeah i
see and i don't know i mean perhaps you
see this too uh maybe it's just because
i'm looking for like-mindedness in a
sense i think about the internet and i
think about youtube and i think about um
audiobooks now even like just how
quickly
are you know
or how quickly what we are humans have
been able to experience all this
spiritual growth because of technology
like the fact that i'm able to while i'm
you know vacuuming and doing laundry i
can be listening to ramdas in my ear and
then it's going to suggest me another
one and you know like if
like my algorithms
know me so well on youtube it's just
like it feeds me so much great spiritual
stuff but i i also see um
other friends who
who do take it uh like more of a deep
dive more you know more let's say more
down to um like star seeds and right
you know like really identifying with
with empaths and stuff and
i'm not saying there's anything anything
wrong with this at all i feel like it's
all kind of a doorway to the same thing
um but but so so i do find it very
interesting what the internet is doing
for us like how many people are being
let's say awakened or finding some sort
of spiritual journey or some sort of um
you know narrowing of path because of
the internet because of technology which
makes me think that it's
you know the way that everything is you
know the tao of things it makes you
think oh okay we're supposed to have
technology then or it's i i don't know
so what do you think about um the state
of technology now and like how many
people are coming to realize some sort
of inner being within themselves because
of it
yeah that's a really great question and
i think that when it comes to our
technologies one of the things that you
pointed out is it's great and that we're
able to be based on what our algorithms
are we're able to be fed information
that's like-minded so if you watch a
video of rom dust you might also be fed
like alan watts and you might you know
and and you might just go through a
playlist of like-minded stuff um but
then the contrary is also true if you're
watching videos that's related to
um a lot of the things that is being fed
by media then you're gonna receive that
as well so i think when it comes to
technologies
remembering that you also have an inner
technology as well is what's gonna help
you to use the outer technology right
like it's when we think that
it's only this outer technology that
that does it um that's going to connect
us is when we lose sight of our own
internal technology so what's our
internal technology um it's our
consciousness it's our heart it's our
bodies it's learning how to trust our
own intuitive wisdom when we can learn
our own internal technologies and
sharpen those skills we're going to be
able we're going to be better able to
use our external technologies and we're
going to have a lot more discernment and
what information we're feeding ourselves
and and all of that i don't know if that
answers your question
yeah yeah i mean it certainly kind of
does the way that i ask questions is
awfully a bit of a rambling statement
that i trail off into so whatever you
can pick up on i'm appreciative of um so
yeah i i think that
it's just it's just very interesting to
me to look at the different stages of my
life like
before i really thought of anything
spiritual like the way that i just never
really i like i never disliked it i
never
um thought that it was you know
completely wrong i feel like i was like
a casual atheist maybe but i just never
really contemplated it very much so who
i was for that many years of my life and
then for the few years of my life where
i discovered it and i had awakened this
thing within me you know i felt like i
was connecting with my soul i started
understanding what that meant i had a
lot of um i was doing a lot of like
kundalini yoga i had a lot of like crazy
weird experiences i did a lot of um
hypnosis and uh healing of childhood
trauma and all this stuff spending a lot
of time with myself meditating for long
periods of time it was this wonderful
um wonderful couple years of my life and
i'm very grateful for it but as i'm like
coming out of it now you know i am
coming into this third stage of kind of
taking a little bit of both you know
like your your remember your your buddha
nature and your social security number
you know and it does feel like this like
i'm coming back into this stream and i
have less anxiety and i'm trying less
but things are still working out okay
and oh yeah my perception of reality is
is a lot i'm not gripping it as much i'm
just kind of allowing um so i don't know
it's just i am still experiencing i'm
still going going through the whole
thing you know i think you know we all
are of course experiencing um our stages
of of uh
you know being spiritual
but uh yeah it's it is very fascinating
so so for you
um because you got led there through you
know no
depression and so maybe do you think
that your identity for you was kind of
in your view of your own identity was
incorrect because i think that a lot of
what of our our quarrels of today come
from is uh
we see ourselves as what we really
aren't you know we we
we box ourselves in with our identity
we're like i am this or you are you're a
liberal or you're you're a republican or
you're this or that and i think that
when we can let go of a lot of our
identities is it seems to where
life gets a little bit easier you know
right um yeah so so what do you think
about identity in this like how has your
identity and your perception of not only
your identity but other people's
identities shifted from before than who
you are now
yeah so
when it comes to identity we see
ourselves as what we think not as who we
are and there's a really big difference
with that seeing ourselves as what we
think versus who we really are so when
we talk about identity or when we talk
about ego
in sanskrit it's called ahamkara and it
stands for the eye maker so ego is the
eye maker so a lot of times when we hear
the word ego we think of oh like you're
such a cocky you know you're so cocky or
you're so conceited or whatever and we
think of oh that person has a big ego
right that's how we use it in our
mainstream culture but the ego is really
what i identify myself with so um and
that's called the eye maker it's what
makes up your personality and so the ego
is um
things that you identify with in terms
of your so your social status in terms
of your economical status your financial
status in terms of uh your your
roles or your titles your positions in
the world
uh all of this makes up your ego and a
large portion of your ego is also
through external programming so when i
talk about external programming what i
mean is
from
the a young age from when we were little
babies when we were first born it's like
we had camera recorders that we had on
our eyes and we'd record everything that
was happening around us and based on
what was happening around us we absorbed
it into our minds and we took it to be
true so you know if for example
my
future mom-in-law she hates coffee so
she wakes up every morning and she
drinks coffee but every time she drinks
it she's like like i hate those coffee
it's so disgusting and she just freaks
out drinking it so i'm like so why do
you drink it like did your mom drink
coffee and she said yeah every morning
every morning i wake up to the smell of
coffee and i just watch her drink it so
unconsciously she's drinking coffee
every morning because she watched her
mom do it every morning but you see like
when when we're not aware of what we
identify with we actually absorb it into
our human experience and our lived
experience to be true so for me i
identified with um just being a a
student
being an overachiever being a big role
model to my younger siblings and being
the first person in my family to you
know go to college and graduate and all
of that i identified largely with that
and so when i was experiencing
depression and all these things were
happening in my life
despite what was happening i still
forced that identity and that's exactly
what caused me to
just lose my mind at towards the end of
it you know i went through this one
period um it was my junior year in
college where
i
competed in bodybuilding because i was
like okay i've gained so much weight at
this point let me do something to to be
healthy so i did the opposite and i went
to a new extreme so i competed in
bodybuilding i
started an online wellness business at
that time um
i
also was struggling three different jobs
at that time and i was i founded this
board to you know help serve other
people i did all these things in a short
abbreviated period of time and you know
pressure might work to create diamonds
but constant applied pressure on a human
being is going to completely burn that
person out and so because i identified
with being this high achiever and um
being a great role model to my younger
siblings and really just like being the
person that breaks through
the um this this sense of uh scarcity
that you feel when you come from being
an immigrant to coming to america
i
i burned out and i didn't have anything
left to me so what we identify with is
really really powerful and the other
thing that i want to note here
to something that you said earlier jake
is something about killing the ego right
we i think sometimes in the mainstream
self-help culture we talk about um the
ego as if it's a really bad thing but
the truth is we actually need our ego
like if you didn't have your ego jake
you wouldn't have a personality you
wouldn't have all these lived
experiences that matter to you that make
you who you are today and we wouldn't
even be able to have this highly
engaging conversation and vice versa
right and so your ego is necessary it's
part of your path the problem is when
you don't know how to befriend the ego
or you don't know how to offer it the
types of internal technologies that it
needs in order to thrive that's when the
ego starts believing more information
from the unconscious part of the mind
versus the conscious part of the mind or
the super conscious part of the mind so
it's one of the things that i talk about
is the three levels of consciousness so
the unconscious part of the mind makes
up 98
of the way that we think it's our it's
our past traumas it's our um limiting
beliefs it's our learned behaviors
that's our unconscious mind the
conscious part of the mind is two
percent of our mind and it's what we're
presently aware of right now so if
that's 98 of our mind the unconscious
and then our ego is majorly going to
come from the unconscious part of the
mind so really our work in the spiritual
journey is to undo what's in the
unconscious mind bring it to the
conscious so that we can have a present
experience and that's what a lot of the
work that rom dos or you know alan watts
i i love the two of them because their
views on spirituality is very grounding
it's not
you know i think there's a place for
talking about starseeds and galaxies and
and other beings like aliens and and
there's there's a place for all of that
and so the people who are um on that
journey um you know they they teach
completely different things for for me
however and what i like to teach and
understand is how can i incorporate
spirituality with my human experience
because i'm here to have a lived
experience i'm not here to be somewhere
else that i'm not
yeah wow wow yeah yeah um i i was
thinking about yeah we all kind of
all these different views of you know
whether we think it's uh starseeds or
we're listening to ramdas or we're into
philosophy or into somehow we find it
through science and quantum physics or
all these different past religions
they're all kind of pointing to the same
thing i think about
i i have one one of my one of my um
friends she's uh she she does identify
as a starseed in this whole thing and i
don't understand it completely but when
she speaks about it and when we talk
about these sorts of things the whole
time inside i'm like yeah totally i i
get you i understand what you're saying
like it's i'm never i think often we get
caught up in trying to like what's the
capital t truth because we can't speak
about anything other than that it's like
we're just we're pointing to things
within our inner experience that like if
you can just look past the words and
understand what they're really saying we
can really connect with one another oh
yeah it's the same thing and that's why
i honor each and every person i say that
everybody here
there's nothing to compare to everybody
here is a unique expression of the
divine so without that person that
focuses on you know starseeds or
palladians or past life lemire you know
aquarius things without that person or
without the person that's talking about
grounded spirituality
there's there's going to be a missing
element to how we evolve human
consciousness right and so we need all
those different elements we we are all
unique expressions of the divine so for
example you know if you're buying a
house you can't close on your property
without you know if you were borrowing
money you would need the mortgage lender
and you would need to have um an
attorney read over your documents and
the realtor like everybody is playing
their part in order for you to close on
this house for example um i know like
housing and everything is super popular
right now so i'm using that example um
so everybody needs to be able to play
their role and do it really well in
order for the final outcome to be
achieved so the way that i look at it is
that um the the the goal of life is just
to experience um
god within ourselves and and evolve
humanity and consciousness in that way
and we do that by each having our own
different expressions and so god plays
hide-and-go-seek through each and every
person and it's up to you to be able to
have the lens and the perception to see
that in people and that's why when i
come across you know my cashier a
cashier or you know a man that's playing
music in the parking lot to raise money
for um paying hospital bills because his
wife has cancer or a homeless person
sitting on the street or a janitor i see
them in a completely different light
than what their identity is and because
of that i've received so much value in
my life from interacting with people and
seeing them as that
yes yeah yeah so do you
before you kind of were in touch with
your more spiritual side did you have a
different perspective in those same
situations
so like if you saw a homeless person did
would you would you think of them maybe
with more um
maybe
like unconscious pity or indifference or
maybe judgment i'm not sure if you did
but yeah curious i said no at first but
i do remember a pivotal moment and i
remember it very clearly that changed my
my whole perspective when i was young
before i had a more spiritual
perspective so when i was around 12
years old it was a really cold um winter
day and this is in massachusetts my
cousin was driving a a really small
it's it's like one of those race cars
there's two door cars and the two of
them were in the front and they're very
tiny
and um the four of us were in the back
and
we drove by main street and there was
this woman wearing um a really like she
was wearing a skirt and tall boots like
long boots and she had her you know her
thighs skin showing and
and i judged her and i called her a oh
like look at that prostitute over there
with that guy you know like um why would
she be why would she be wearing that you
know like when it's so cold outside and
everything
so i judged her and that's just from my
learned environment and so we drive up
this hill and now we're stuck
and now my two cousins in the front like
they're both super tight like we're all
super tiny we're like trying to push it
and you know a car is not budging so
we're just trapped at this point and
it's freezing cold
and
before you know it the woman that i
judge with the
boots and you know the heels and
everything and her man
were the two people that came up and
helped us push the car and was so sweet
and so kind and so compassionate and if
it wasn't for them we would have been
stranded there and i learned like i
cried because i felt so bad that i
judged this other person and i will
never forget that day i will never
forget what she taught me in that moment
so from that experience i learned not to
judge people and i learned to
approach people with compassion and
kindness because if it was true that she
was a prostitute if it wasn't that's
none of my business like her what she
identifies with is none of my business
but who she is as a human being and that
sense of love and happiness that we are
all endowed with that's deep within us
is there
and again like like god is there right
so who am i to judge her and so from
that experience every homeless person
that i encountered i approached with a
place of love i literally would just go
um i would buy them something to eat i
would sit down with them and i would
have a conversation and through those
experiences i learned so much and when i
was actually going through my years of
depression i
felt like the people who were homeless
understood me the most i found i found
this sense of um
understanding and this sense of
togetherness in homeless people versus
the friends and the people who are
around me
wow wow wow that's awesome yes uh again
with ramdas uh
how is this also just god dressed in
drag
you know
he would often say stuff like that um
learning that someone that was annoying
him is actually just god dressed in drag
i like that yeah isn't that so isn't
that so great because when we you know
when we
you know maybe it's because we're caught
in our identities and so we're seeing
our other people's identities in
contrast to who we think we are so we're
like reaffirming our identity oh i'm
this person and i know that because
they're that person you know it helps us
make it feel feel safe in our own selves
but it's a interesting little little bit
of
karmic learning that that may have been
happening to you there you know uh
because we
it it's it's again you know we we meet
each other on the wrong level so often
and we see that a lot in the media in
the news and all these things we meet
each other we say you're this and i'm
that and we don't get along whatever but
like if you
i i'd imagine now um when you would
first see someone say they're dressed in
the same exact outfit like tomorrow if
you're walking around you see someone
dress the same outfit you're not even
probably going to consciously think like
oh that's a that's a prostitute or
that's or i would have thought you
probably would have just if you have an
interaction with them you're just going
to be present and you're just going to
be with them whenever they have to offer
not offer you as if you're
taking something but but whatever
they show up as is who you who you get
to interact with you know like so if
you're polite to someone they'll often
polite back you know but if you assume
that someone is this other thing you
might accidentally come up come off at
them you know like if you're treating
someone like a prostitute maybe they're
gonna respond like a prostitute exactly
and it's unconscious and you're not
aware of it so today you know my i think
my fiance gets to see it the most
because he spends the most time around
me but all
like the the other day we got groceries
and the guy that was bagging our stuff
and checked us out like he ran to the um
the front of trader joe's where all the
flowers were and he gave me flowers like
before i left and i just have things
like that happen often because of just
the the interactions that and i'm not
trying that's the thing is when you're
just present and you're yourself you
don't have to try you don't have to try
to give value you don't have to try to
make someone's day just by you being you
people feel that and they experience it
and along the other lines of what you
were saying um
i think that
approaching people from a place of
giving them your present attention
and awareness versus judgment
although the mind is made to judge right
so like don't judge yourself for judging
if you're judging because like that's
what the mind does that's literally what
the mind does but but be aware of it
because when you're aware of it you can
see how you're approaching people and
situations
the thing i want to say about this is
this is more important now than ever
because what i'm witnessing in the
landscape that we're living in right now
is that
there is a constant it's like a constant
injection of fear from things that we're
absorbing from the media right so
whether it's politics like if you're a
republican or or i'm democratic or vice
versa or if you got vaccinated or i
didn't or if somebody um you know
believes in wearing mass or somebody
doesn't what i'm noticing is there's so
much divide and separation
based on these judgments and we're we're
we're almost getting to a place where
we're losing sight of human connection
and being present with each other
without these other labels that are
there and it's making us sicker because
when we don't have human connection when
we don't feel connected to ourselves
when our mind is so focused on trying to
be right and trying to impose what we
believe on other people
we are literally extracting ourselves
from being present within our own bodies
and having a more present experience and
i would say the greatest gift of life is
to be present to actually receive what's
in front of you and so
i don't invite anybody listening to this
you know if you feel like you know
you're coming from a really good place
and you want to save the people around
you for example again i think a lot of
us come from a place of great intentions
right
when it comes to all these labels um but
the best thing that you can do is to do
what works for you and what serves you
and to offer compassion and
understanding to the people around you
and when you do this you get to learn
from the other person they get to learn
from you and we evolve as humanity
versus you know if you don't believe
this then you know you suck and you're
gonna die you know it's it's such a
completely different energy how do we
evolve in that way
yeah yeah yeah santa you're you're
speaking is poetry uh you're saying so
many like your sentences are just
following each other so well i'm just
like yep
heck yeah yeah heck yeah sister i'm like
i'm loving it um great great fire stuff
okay so how do we become aware that this
is the biggest thing right um you're a
meditation teacher and i think that's
really the essence of of meditation as i
study it um a bit more in my own
practice and and learn about the
different types uh my definition of
meditation i feel like kind of changes
so um i think that's what probably one
of the bigger things of meditation is is
becoming aware and then after some time
you start to form like a natural
distance with the awareness from from
your actions or or the observation of
your thoughts so in your um in your
world as a meditation teacher like like
what
so so what what type of meditation do
you typically teach and then how would
you someone who doesn't meditate or they
don't really maybe they this intrigues
them but they haven't really experienced
much meditation or gaining awareness or
being able to see when they maybe
unconsciously judging someone what's the
introduction to that like how do you
normally kind of explain that
yeah so
just to speak to what's present right
now
i would say that
the way that we would become more
present or more aware of ourselves is by
reconnecting back with our bodies
i think that that conversation is so
much more important to have and it's not
it's contrary to what you think
meditation is so typically when people
think of meditation they think you know
you sit down you close your eyes and
then you
focus your thoughts or you don't think
at all right just like get rid of your
thoughts right
turn them off right um but just like
your heart is beating involuntarily just
like
when you eat food your stomach breaks
down all your food for you right like
your brain is here to think it's here to
make judgments in in order for you you
know if you didn't make a judgment we
wouldn't be having this conversation
right now right because you had to make
a judgment on whether or not you want
certain people on your podcast or not
and vice versa right and so our brains
are here to help us and and we need our
brains to make judgments however
it's not about
the thinking it's about getting back in
touch with your body and uh so the
meditation that i teach um i call it
shanta real meditation and it's a body
of wisdom that i've developed over the
past nine years from learning this work
i learned meditation through my teacher
who is leonard pearl mudder and he
studied from a teacher
he's a disciple of swami rama who
was the first one of the first yogis to
come over from india to america
and he had scientists put ekgs all over
his body in order to see or or believe
that he can actually control his
internal pressure temperature and
everything his heart rate his heartbeat
he can turn it off he can turn it on and
so they did that and they were able to
recognize that wait a second um this
yogi is proving to us the opposite of
what we think is true this yogi is
showing us that it's actually true that
the mind and the body are connected as
one whereas in um the western world we
see it as two completely separate things
which is why often times when we go and
we see doctors it's it's mostly focused
on um finding resolves to the symptom
versus seeing the holistic picture right
and so
um that was who my teacher studied from
and then he initiated me into this
tradition and so um this meditation
tradition is very it's it's yoga science
it's very much focused on how do you uh
integrate being a human
while also having the spiritual
experience at the same time and so
there's breathing practices that we
learn in order to become one with the
divine and that's called yoga science
yoga stands for union and all of life is
really this science experiment like i if
more people recognize their life as an
experiment we would just have no
pressure like we would just say it's
just an experiment right like i'm gonna
try it it would be so fun exactly so i'm
gonna try this and if it works for me
great like i'm gonna eat you know this
cheesecake if it works for me great but
if i feel bad and i can eat it again
right
so it's this big experiment so i studied
from my teacher
and through my studies with my teacher
i was able to go into deeper practices
within myself and that's when i i came
up with the body of wisdom called shanta
royale which stands for the royal path
of peace so when i was initiated in the
into this tradition my teacher gifted me
the name shanta which stands for peace
and then when i started to create shanta
rayal meditation you know the intention
of that is to answer this question of
you know
does one have to be a monk in order to
meditate or
uh can we be
bill payers householders have kids and
and you know be multi-millionaires and
still be able to experience a sense of
peace because when you're on this path
of spirituality you constantly think you
have to give
and sacrifice one thing for another and
you don't think that you're actually
allowed to have this human experience i
find and so um the meditation i teach is
all about reintegrating yourself back
into this human experience and being
very grounded so one of the first things
that we do is learning how to reconnect
with your body
you know we've been so far removed from
our bodies even to this day we're
constantly you know on our phones which
take us literally out of our bodies i i
want more people to pay attention to
this pay attention to if you're
breathing fully when you're on your
phone or are you just holding your
breath or are you just breathing from
your chest right when we were babies we
would breathe from our diaphragms we
would inhale deeply and exhale if you
have babies watch a way that your baby
breathes because that's how you were
breathing you were able to self-regulate
as a baby however when we got older and
the more that we inundate ourselves with
these external devices without being in
tuned with our internal technologies now
what we're doing is we're being more
further removed from our bodies we're
not even paying attention to how the
breath is going into our bodies and
we're cutting our the oxygen that comes
into the cells really short
and so
part of it is learning how to slow down
learning how to create a lifestyle
around what your core values are and
what's important to you and setting
healthy boundaries so it's one of the
main things that i teach like super
beginner level set healthy boundaries
learn how to have tough conversations
because if you keep saying yes to things
in your life when your whole body is
just like it's hurting it's saying no i
don't want to do this and you do that
over again and again and again
when you go and you sit down in your
meditation you're not going to be able
to go there you're not going to be able
to experience that sense of peace that
you want because your body is so high on
adrenaline and it's so burnt out that
that level of intention that is required
for you to be in a more focused space
it's not going to be there so before i
get into any of that you know i teach
people how to move their bodies and how
to get comfortable with their body so
they can feel safe in their bodies and
then we go into the the meditation but
that's all part of meditation in itself
yeah yeah so do you find for me
uh i was often i was a bodybui well i
wasn't competing or anything but i
enjoyed bodybuilding i was i liked being
big i liked lifting heavy weights all
this stuff
and then now i i mean i always liked
running but i like running a lot now i
love doing a lot of yoga um i'm not
caring about as much what my physique
looks like but more how i feel um and
and the difference from that is just
just so profound did you have anything
like that from when you were
bodybuilding versus kind of your do you
do yoga or anything that sort of stuff
now
i do but i don't do yoga like i don't do
the asana practices and things like that
that you learn in a regular yoga class i
like qigong and i do
i do movements where it's
i'm twisting the body in a way where
it's massaging my lymphatic system and
it's like it's building muscle at the
same time because it's really natural
strong movements but yeah that
transition was interesting for me to go
from lifting heavy weights to you know
not doing that all i don't i don't even
go to the gym i do a lot of practices
where it's just with my own body and
i've been the same weight you know since
whereas when i was bodybuilding i would
fluctuate up and down and i would just
either feel so insecure that i was going
up or down it was just too much and so
now what i find is i'm i say self-care
is being self-aware so i'm just aware of
what my body needs and and i do it and i
just listen to it and then it tells me
you know what practices to do or um
what's going to feel good but yeah i
haven't done that hardcore bodybuilding
type of workout in a really long time i
like i do love running i love
qigong
which is a very ancient movement
practice as well that strengthens your
body up from the inside out and
i love short bursts of
movements as well
interval training so short interval
trainings but mostly just free weights
free body movements
yep heck yeah i'm a lot with you there
i've been um i've had a gym membership
for last couple months and i'll kind of
go a couple times a week
but it's not incredibly tough it's
nothing like i used to lift you know
it's just i'm just trying to feel good
i'm trying to feel like my posture is
supported yeah um
you know and then i'll hit the sauna
afterwards at the gym too that's always
feeling i feel really um you know i try
to meditate in there as often as i can
just try to focus on the breath you know
um and that gets you that gets you
pretty dang grounded yeah because we we
really don't notice how far off base we
get when we're off base you know it's
like
if we could snap our fingers and feel
instantly like just for five seconds
okay here's how i feel hungover for five
seconds feeling hungover and then right
back to how you are you'll be like oh my
god i'm never drinking again yeah you
notice the contrast of it you know um
and we i think we do the same thing when
it comes to our phones you know it makes
sense while we're in it and yeah we we
think we had the the free will to pick
up our phone and you know scroll through
this thing and now we're mad like we
want to be mad we made the choice to
choose this thing so it's mad so so it
seems justified um but we kind of
disconnect from the fact that these
companies have studied humans they know
all about our brains and how they work
and the goal is to keep us on the
platform right and so the things that
we're reading on our phones and our
social media feeds um are designed to
keep our attention but
it you know in it it
i don't know purposely or maybe
inadvertently also affects our bodily
functions you know it activates our
brain stem and it makes us in the fear
response and think about um i read this
book
i mentioned on podcast a couple days ago
too but the z technique or the zifa
meditation by emily fletcher um and she
she kind of described i think it's been
said before but she kind of describes
you know do you think your toenails are
growing when you're running from a lion
like do you or do you think your body is
prioritizing okay let's send blood to
these these locations so we can empower
our limbs to get away from this lion you
know if you're in a fear response where
you need to keep yourself safe not your
whole internal system isn't working how
it should be so you're not prioritizing
um digestion you know like our food
system is so
complicated and crappy in so many ways
like we need all of the focus on our
digestive system that we can get but if
we're here fighting with someone who
you know
loves the opposite president that we
like it's going to put us in this fear
response and then our internal system is
not working at an optimal level and if
you're doing that eight hours a day you
just put a big hinge on your health so
yeah
people
i'm always trying to point to like the
like hey don't you see it don't you see
that like isn't that important like
don't you see how they're kind of
tricking you you know how the how the
the systems of capitalism are kind of
like hurting you even though you think
that it's bringing you joy and
entertainment yeah yeah
yeah you know i go through i go through
that that kind of like toggle sometimes
because i actually when i started to
learn meditation i shut down all of my
social media channels for a whole year
and it was
it was amazing it was it was so amazing
it was like
focused like right like it's deep focus
deep presentness even if you have good
boundaries with your phone i've gotten
to a place where i definitely have great
boundaries with my phone i use it for a
lot of things with my business and just
sharing some of these messages right but
even then the fact that it's just there
you know it's like calling for your for
your attention so sometimes i toggle
back and forth between not having a
social media at all because of i'm so
committed to the work that i'm doing
that you know maybe that's another
experiment that i should have
you know down down the road and maybe i
will i'm not attached to it but
yeah i think it's about learning how do
you navigate because whether we like it
or not these technologies are are going
to be here and they're going to continue
to advance faster and faster and faster
and faster and faster at the same token
our consciousness is also going to
advance faster and faster and faster so
it's really just about learning how to
use it without letting it use you and
that's really where that fine line is
and where it gets it gets hard sometimes
it gets a little um smoky
yeah yeah absolutely that's a that's a
fire way of putting it too like not
letting the technology use you but
learning how to use it you know um it's
a tool it doesn't have to be a mind
control object
but uh so so you've mentioned a couple
times
boundaries and i would love to it's
fresh in my mind yesterday um i was
talking with the co-worker um and he's
such an awesome guy he's like just very
um
empathetic very kind very sweet very
open um and we i don't remember how we
kind of got on the conversation but uh
he's basically saying like you know he
he recognizes hey you know it's kind of
jaded but at this point in my life i
kind of recognize um when people are
gonna be like i don't want them to use
me like i'm so nice and so open i don't
want them to take from me because
sometimes you'll have people like you
know hey oh oh hey you need a ride man
like no problem i got you but then all
of a sudden you're giving them a ride
monday through friday you know you know
those sorts of things so he's he was
kind of just mentioning um that he he's
trying to learn the difference between
um
we were kind of talking difference
between boundaries and barriers
and kind of how you can be open and
loving and be accepting and like allow
what's going to happen but also know
when it's okay to like all right let's
let's let's put our let's put our foot
down like let's uh let's let's have this
boundary so can you speak a little bit
more on on boundaries maybe boundaries
versus barriers if you use that
terminology at all
yeah i'll talk about how about i'll talk
about boundaries i don't use that that
terminology a lot but i have heard of it
so when it comes to boundaries in the
way that i see it
it's about getting really clear about
what your core values are and what
matters to you when you get clear about
what your core values are what you'll
begin to see even more clearly what
universe and god will show you is what
is not important to you and what you're
making a really big deal out of that
doesn't line up or areas where you're
seeking for other people's approval
which is why you extend yourself and you
extend yourself i think a lot of us
because we have grown up through
um patriarchal programming where a lot
of the information that we learned is
rooted in capitalism like you talked
about uh it we we feel like in order to
get somewhere in society
we have to deliver a lot of value in
order to receive a certain something in
return so like if you go back to school
you know you
go to school you start school when the
bell rings ding ding ding like start
school and then the bell rings again you
go into second period third period
fourth right
and then um you it's like constant
reiteration of of how we're supposed to
be learning like you show up you do the
work and then you move on to a higher
grade now you're going to reach another
level same thing like when you're
you know in when you're done with high
school you get your graduation
certificate you know if you do bad on a
piece of paper you get an f so we have
literally been trained through these
systems in order to
learn how to deliver a ton of value aka
do really good work otherwise we're not
going to be of importance to the people
around us so we have to first understand
that this is rooted deeply in in our in
our wiring and part of this is being
able to recognize that and giving
ourselves a lot of grace and compassion
as to why we constantly extend ourselves
or we say yes to people when we really
mean no or we have a hard time just
setting our boundaries so that's the
first thing and then the second thing
with boundaries is now like
now that you're aware of that notice
what really is important in your life
what are the things that you're
naturally drawn to what are your core
values what's more important to you than
money and why if you answer that
question you know you might you might
say happiness you might say health you
might say joy right those are your core
values now look at all the areas in your
life where you're saying yes to
something when it's really not lining up
with those core values for example if
you had you know negative nancy you know
calls you every sunday to complain about
the same things again and again and
again and you entertain it every time
even though after that one hour
conversation your energy is just
completely drained
right but you don't know how to say no
um does that line up with your core
value of happiness or health or joy the
answer is no so if the answer is no why
are you entertaining this actually allow
yourself to sit in that for a little bit
where is that coming from right
when we do this type of work what we're
actually doing is we're giving ourselves
the the the ability to reprogram the
decisions that we're making and where
they're coming from so maybe if you look
at this a little bit more um maybe it
was from when you were 10 years old you
know um you got made fun of because you
were um
you you weren't talking like most of the
times when everybody else was talking so
now you always feel like you have to
have something to say and you have to
entertain every conversation that's
coming your way
right so like when you give yourself
space to do this you're actually going
to be really clear around why you
entertain those things and why you don't
set boundaries it's going to be easier
for you to set those boundaries and
you're not going to feel that sense of
guilt or shame that comes with setting
boundaries so a lot of times when i'm
teaching people how to set boundaries or
how to have tough conversations there's
always a sense of like fear that comes
up because they think they're going to
hurt the other person's feelings but
what happens is when you get really
clear on where this came from you can
communicate to people from a place of
love like you know hey nancy i
understand that you're going through a
lot in your life right now but
like these right now i'm really focused
on xyz and it's really important to me
and i also want to be able to give you
my attention
however now is not the time like does
does this time work for you instead and
when we talk let's focus on xyz instead
or can we talk about this instead
or even just being honest with people i
think that when we set boundaries we're
giving ourselves and that person an
opportunity to be honest to say hey like
we've been talking about the same thing
every single week and it seems like it's
not getting you anywhere how else do you
think i can support you right um and and
just being clear with people because
most people that cross your boundaries
don't know that they're actually
crossing them
um
yeah i really like that yeah i uh i
think of a i had a person in my life who
at some point i kind of had to set some
boundaries and basically
hey i don't want to talk about this
negative stuff all the time like you
don't seem to really listen you know you
come to me seems like solutions but when
we try to talk through it or i try to
give you a different lens it doesn't
seem like you're listening and um so
essentially the it kind of turned into
it was a little bit of a kind of a tense
conversation at that moment but then i
did notice over the course of the weeks
when i would talk to this person um they
seem to be a little more reciprocating
to to listening to what i had to say or
trying to be positive or trying to
not just end with uh and here's all this
thing i'm putting on you but they're
they would try to flip a sort of
positive lens on it you know and not
that i was just trying to like hey see
it my way my way is the only way but it
was i was making them aware that they
were kind of draining my energy that i
was really not i didn't really want to
be in this place to just kind of like
take on your your whole day you know i
just kind of like wanted to protect you
know protect and
be within my own energy at that point in
my life so yeah i noticed that after a
little while they seem to kind of
kind of okay i i get it you know so
having that conversation is helpful um
sandy we're getting up here in time i
would like to try to squeeze one more
question in here if you're cool with it
yeah let's do it yeah i ask i ask guests
this one fairly often simply is
what does the world need more of right
now
well the first answer that comes up is
love love and peace like if we can
if we can learn to
to view everything no matter how painful
it is no matter how much you don't
believe in it no matter how opposing it
is if you can view it through the lens
of love then love is going to teach you
something because love is also the most
ancient traveler it has been here long
before we've been here it's the reason
that we're here and it's going to be
here long before we're gone and so in
order for us to be instruments of love
we have to be able to view the world
through that perspective no matter how
much we disagree with the things that
are happening around us and the more
that we can do that the better teachers
and just people we can be in general
because we're all here to teach and
we're also all here to be students and
learn as well
yeah we're here to take the curriculum
instruments of love that was a wonderful
thing that you just said i like that um
okay so so
summarizing your um your website let's
make sure we send everybody where can
they find more of your stuff more of
your talks like where can we get your
info where can we find you
yeah you can find everything on
sandyvo.com so
s-a-n-d-y-b is victory bsnvictoryo.com
and you'll connect you with every every
program um service there's a free
meditation right on there
my podcast and then uh other podcasts
that i've been on we're working on that
right now and then um my instagram all
of that is on there as well
okay i love it i'll include it in that
description what's the name of your
podcast one more time it's prosperous
the podcast
love it all right everybody check that
out check out sandyvo i'll include the
info in the description thank you so
much for your time i really appreciate
it this was a wonderful conversation
thanks so much for having me jake i
really enjoyed it yeah yeah all right
well take care listeners take care of
yourself love yourself stretch drink a
little bit of water and uh look around
you got you got life right here be here
take care see you later sandy
at what age
[Music]
knowledge is power
you